Mahmoud Assran (Mido)

Montreal, QC, Canada

mahmoud.assran@mail.mcgill.ca midoassran.ca ♂

Overview

I am a final year PhD student at McGill University ☑ and Mila ☑, and a Visiting Researcher at Meta AI (FAIR) ☑ investigating self-supervised representation learning of visual features.

I have a strong first-author publication record in top-tier conferences and journals — ICML-{19,20}, NeurIPS-20, Proc. IEEE-20, IEEE TAC-21, ICCV-21 Oral, ECCV-22 — along with demonstrated theoretical **(T)** and empirical **(E)** contributions: **(T)** provided first non-convergence proof of Nesterov Momentum with mini-batch gradients under strong convexity (ICML-20); **(E)** currently hold state-of-the-art in semi-supervised classification on ImageNet-1K (Masked Siamese Networks, ECCV-22).

I am also actively involved in professional service, and have served as an Expert Reviewer at NeurIPS-21 and ICML-21, received *Best Reviewer* awards at NeurIPS-20, ICML-{20,21}, and received the *One of 12 Outstanding Reviewers* award at AAAI-20.

Research Interests

Self-supervised representation learning, visual perception, deep learning, parallel and distributed optimization.

Research Experience

Facebook, Al Research	2017-present
-----------------------	--------------

Visiting Researcher, PhD 2019-present Research Assistant, PhD 2018-2019 Research Intern, PhD Summer 2018 Graduate Researcher 2017-2018

McGill, Computer Networks Research Lab Summer 2016

Undergraduate Researcher in Engineering

Manulife, RED Lab Summer 2015

Solutions Prototype Developer

Education

PhD, Electrical and Computer Eng. 2018-present

McGill University, Mila - Quebec Al Institute, Montréal, Canada

Advisors: Mike Rabbat, Mark Coates

CGPA: 4.0/4.0 Doctoral Awards:

\$150,000 Vanier Scholarship, NSERC

\$105,000 Alexander Graham Bell Scholarship, NSERC

\$72,000 McGill Engineering Doctoral Award \$48,000 Les Vadasz Doctoral Fellowship

\$3,000 Graduate Mobility Award

MEng, Electrical and Computer Eng. 2017–2018

McGill University, Montréal, Canada

Advisor: Mike Rabbat

Graduate Excellence Fellowship

CGPA: 3.9/4.0

BEng, Electrical and Computer Eng. McGill University, Montréal, Canada

Advisor: Mike Rabbat

Dean's Honours & Top 5% of Faculty

CGPA: 3.9/4.0

Preprints

- [18] M. Assran, Q. Duval, P. Vincent, I. Misra, P. Bojanowski, M. Rabbat, *Y. LeCun, *N. Ballas. Self-Supervised Learning from Images with a Joint-Embedding Predictive Architecture. Preprint, 2022.
- [17] M. Assran, R. Balestriero, Q. Duval, P. Bojanowski, I. Misra, F. Bordes, P. Vincent, M. Rabbat, N. Ballas. The Hidden Uniform Cluster Prior in Self-Supervised Learning.

 Preprint, 2022.
- [16] S. Mo, J. Su, C. Ma, M. Assran, I. Misra, L. Yu, S. Bell RoPAWS: Robust Semi-supervised Representation Learning from Uncurated Data. Preprint, 2022.
- [15] S. Sodhani, O. Delalleau, M. Assran, K. Sinha, N. Ballas, M. Rabbat. A Closer Look at Codistillation for Distributed Training. Preprint, 2020.

Conference & Journal Papers

- [13] M. Assran, M. Caron, I. Misra, P. Bojanowski, F. Bordes, P. Vincenet, A. Joulin, M. Rabbat, N. Ballas. Masked Siamese Networks for Label-Efficient Learning.

 European Conference on Computer Vision (ECCV), 2022.
- [12] PA. McRae, P. Parthasarathi, M. Assran, S. Chandar.
 Memory Augmented Optimizers for Deep Learning.
 International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR), 2022.
- [11] M. Assran, M. Caron, I. Misra, P. Bojanowski, A. Joulin, *N. Ballas, *M. Rabbat. Semi-Supervised Learning of Visual Features by Non-Parametrically Predicting View Assignments with Support Samples. (Oral, Top 3% of papers)
 International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV), 2021.
- [10] M. Assran, M. Rabbat.

Asynchronous Gradient Push.

IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control (IEEE TAC), 2021.

- [9] M. Assran, A. Aytekin, H. Feyzmahdavian, M. Johansson, M. Rabbat. Advances in Asynchronous Parallel and Distributed Optimization. Proceedings of the IEEE (Proc. IEEE), 2020.
- [8] M. Assran, M. Rabbat.

On the Convergence of Nesterov's Accelerated Gradient Method in Stochastic Settings. International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML), 2020.

[7] M. Assran, J. Romoff, N. Ballas, J. Pineau, M. Rabbat.

Gossip-based Actor-Learner Architectures for Deep Reinforcement Learning.

Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS), 2019.

[6] M. Assran, N. Loizou, N. Ballas, M. Rabbat.

Stochastic Gradient Push for Distributed Deep Learning.

International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML), 2019.

[5] M. Assran, M. Rabbat.

An Empirical Comparison of Multi-Agent Optimization Algorithms.

IEEE Global Conference on Signal and Information Processing (IEEE GlobalSIP), 2017.

Workshop Papers

[4] M. Assran, N. Ballas, L. Castrejon, M. Rabbat.

Contrastive Pre-Training with Task Information.

Self-Supervised Learning Workshop, NeurIPS, 2020.

[3] M. Assran, N. Loizou, N. Ballas, M. Rabbat.

Stochastic Gradient Push.

Systems for ML Workshop, NeurIPS, 2018.

[2] M. Assran, M. Rabbat.

Convergence of Asynchronous Subgradient Push Under Bounded Delays.

Workshop on Advances in Distributed and Large-Scale Optimization, ECC, 2018. *Invited.

Theses

[1] M. Assran.

Asynchronous Subgradient Push: Fast, Robust, and Scalable Multi-Agent Optimization.

Masters Thesis, McGill University Libraries, 2018.

Professional Activities

Conference Reviewing

Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)

2023 Reviewer

European Conference on Computer Vision (ECCV)

2022 Emergency Reviewer

International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML)

2021 Expert Reviewer (Best Reviewer Award)

2020 Reviewer (Top Reviewer Award)

2019 Reviewer

Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS)

2021 Expert Reviewer

2020 Reviewer (Best Reviewer Award)

2019 Reviewer

Association for the Advancement of Artificial Intelligence Conference (AAAI)

2020 Reviewer (One of 12 Outstanding Reviewers Award)

International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR)

2022 Reviewer

2021 Reviewer

International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS)

2022 Reviewer

IFAC World Congress 2020 Reviewer

Journal Reviewing

Automatica

Journal of Artificial Intelligence Research (JAIR)

SIAM Journal on Optimization (SIOPT)

IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control

IEEE Transactions on Signal Processing

IEEE Transactions on Control of Network Systems

IEEE Transactions on Signal and Information Processing over Networks

IEEE Signal Processing Magazine

ReScience ICLR Reproducibility Challenge

Community Service

Youth Engagement Through Engineering (YETE)

2020-present

Co-Founder and Managing Director

Founded a not-for-profit corporation to benefit Canadian communities by advancing youth education and facilitating pathways for youth to post-secondary education; especially for indigenous youth in Quebec. To date, during the COVID-19 pandemic, we have developed and piloted a successful online afterschool program at FACE high school in the English Montreal School Board (EMSB), focused on project-based learning and constructivist learning methodologies.

Engineers Without Borders, Youth Engagement

2013-2020

Director & Facilitator

Lead the Youth Engagement Venture in the Engineers Without Borders Montreal chapter. Developed an interdisciplinary semester-long program and taught high school students, in class, once a week, for their entire school semester. Personally delivered this curriculum, with the support of my team, at 5 different schools in the English Montreal School Board (EMSB), as well as at an indigenous school, on the Kahnawake Mohawk Reserve. Worked closely with school boards, students, teachers, and principals to maximize learning outcomes. Provided pro bono consulting services for the McGill Engineering Department and the McGill Administration and Enrolment Services to develop culturally relevant education programs for indigenous high school students with the ultimate goal of increasing post-secondary enrolment, and established several long-term collaborations. Also provided pro bono consulting services for the EMSB to integrate more project-based learning across schools in Montreal.

International RoboCup

2018

Judge (Poster & Presentations)

Conducted interviews with \sim 60 international teams from over 30 countries, and judged poster presentations to assess qualities such as novelty, team-working skills, poster design, and technical impact.

Nonlinear Optimization (MATH 560)

2018

Grader

Served as a grader for Prof. Tim Hoheisel's graduate non-linear optimization class in the math department at McGill University. Graded students' proofs in assignments and midterms.

Signals and Systems (ECSE 221)

2015, 2016

Official Final Exam Review Facilitator

At the request of the department's student society, I volunteered to prepare and conduct the final exam review session for the Signals and Systems (ECSE 221) course at McGill University, for two consecutive years. The sessions typically had \sim 40 students and lasted about 6 hours. We stepped through theoretical topics and practice problems in this time.

Honours & Awards

Vanier Canada Graduate Scholarship

2020

NSERC | \$150,000

Awarded to only 9 doctoral students in Canada in the Computing Sciences over the previous 4 years; the Vanier CGS plays an important role in fulfilling the Government of Canada's Science and Technology strategy to promote the development and application of leading-edge knowledge, support the development of a world class workforce, and attract and retain the world's top graduate students. Awarded to doctoral students who have demonstrated strong leadership skills and a high standard of scholarly achievement in graduate studies in the social sciences and humanities, natural sciences and engineering, and health.

Alexander Graham Bell Canada Graduate Scholarship

2020

NSERC | \$105,000

Ranked 16th out of 1878 doctoral applicants in Canada pursuing research in the natural sciences and engineering. Awarded to the top-ranked doctoral students in Canada, to ensure a reliable supply of qualified personnel to meet the needs of Canada's knowledge economy.

Les Vadasz Doctoral Fellowship

2018

McGill University | \$48,000

Established in 2006 by the Vadasz Family Foundation to recruit outstanding students into the Faculty of Engineering's doctoral degree program.

McGill Engineering Doctoral Award

2018

McGill University | \$72,000

This award aims to recruit the best and brightest new doctoral students from all over the world. Selection for this award is based on the excellence of a student's academic and research record, including publications, presentations and his or her potential to make a major impact on the quality of research in the Faculty of Engineering at McGill University and in the field of engineering.

Graduate Mobility Award

2018

McGill University

To support student engagement in international research experiences outside of McGill, this guaranteed voucher for the Graduate Mobility Award (GMA) helps cover expenses associated with a visit/stay at a research lab, field work abroad, and/or visit with a research collaborator.

Undergraduate Student Masters Award

2017

McGill University | \$35,000

Competitive recruitment funding to assist in attracting and retaining high caliber undergraduate students with demonstrated academic excellence, as well as applied research experience, into the Faculty's research Graduate Programs.

Graduate Excellence Fellowship

2017

McGill University

Nomination for this award is at the discretion of the Department or School. Selection for this award is based on the excellence of a student's academic and research record.

Rhodes Scholar Finalist 2017 University of Oxford One of 12 finalists selected for three available Rhodes Scholarships, an international postgraduate scholarship to study at the University of Oxford. Ian McLachlin Prize for Entrepreneurship in Engineering 2017 McGill University Established in 1998 by Ian McLachlin, B.Eng. 1960, to encourage Engineering students to undertake Entrepreneurial Studies. Awarded by the Faculty of Engineering. Dean's Honour List 2014, 2015, 2016, 2017 McGill University The Dean's Honour List for undergraduate students recognizes those who rank in the top 10% of the Faculty of Engineering, based on the combined GPA for all courses taken during the Fall and Winter terms. Les Vadasz Award in Engineering 2016 McGill University Awarded annually, by the Faculty of Engineering, to a student based on high academic standing with a preference given to an interest in, and contribution towards, engineering sustainability and/or design. Accenture Prize in Engineering and Science 2016 McGill University Awarded by the Faculty Scholarships Committees, upon recommendation of the respective departments, on the basis of academic excellence and demonstrated leadership qualities. Faculty of Engineering Scholarship 2016 McGill University Established in 1992 by the University to provide awards based on academic achievement to students in the top 5% of the Faculty. Granted by the Faculty of Engineering Scholarships Committee based on good academic standing. **Undergraduate Student Research Award** 2016 **NSERC** Undergraduate Student Research Award, granted by the university and the Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada, based on the student's academic record, research aptitude, and merit. John Howard Ambrose Award 2016 McGill University Awarded by the Faculty of Engineering Scholarships Committee on the basis of merit to engineering students. **IEEE Signal Processing Society Winter School Scholarship** 2016 **IEEE Signal Processing Society** Awarded by the IEEE Signal Processing Society on the basis of merit to engineering students. John Green Memorial Award 2016 McGill University For the student with highest standing in the penultimate year of Honours Electrical Engineering. Awarded on the recommendation of the Department. 1st Place Waterloo Hardware Hackathon 2015 Google, O'Reilly, PCH | \$55,000 (Awarded \$5000 cash scholarship and \$50,000 in product services; e.g., manufacturing, incorporation fees, etc.). Developed a solution and a prototype to provide Internet access to developing communities

by utilizing a distributed data mesh with an offline search engine.

Christie Steinmetz Award 2014

McGill University

Awarded to a second year student in Electrical Engineering on the basis of academic performance and demonstration of exceptional promise as an engineer. Awarded on the recommendation of the Department.

McCaig Family Scholarship in Engineering

2014

McGill University

Awarded by the Faculty of Engineering to undergraduate students who have completed at least one year of the B.Eng. program on the basis of high academic standing.

Selected Talks

Masked Siamese Networks for Label-efficient Learning

2022	New York City, US	New York University CILVR Seminar *Invited Talk
2022	New York City, US	Columbia University VIGR Seminar *Invited Talk
2022	Online	Facebook AI Research East Coast All Hands
2022	Online	Facebook East Coast Computer Vision Group
2022	Online	Facebook EMEA Computer Vision Group

Semi-Supervised Learning of Visual Representations

2021	Online	International Computer Vision Talks *Invited Talk
2021	Online	International Conference on Computer Vision
2021	Online	Facebook SSL for Video Group *Invited Talk
2021	Online	Facebook GCD (AI Scaling) Group *Invited Talk

Contrastive Pre-Training with Task Information

2020	Online	Self-Supervised Learning Workshop, NeurIPS
2020	Online	Montreal MLOpt Research Group
2020	Online	Facebook AI Research Global All Hands

On the Convergence of Nesterov's Accelerated Gradient Method in Stochastic Settings

2020	Online	International	l Conference d	on Ma	chine	Learning	(ICML)
------	--------	---------------	----------------	-------	-------	----------	--------

2020 Montreal, CA Montreal MLOpt Research Group

Gossip-based Actor-Learner Architectures for Deep Reinforcement Learning

2020	Online	Aggregate Intellect (ai.science) *Invited Talk
2020	Online	Mila RL Reading Group *Invited Talk
2019	Vancouver, CA	Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS)
2019	Montreal, CA	Montreal Al Symposium (Top 10% of Accepted Papers)

Advancing Artificial Intelligence: Learning Over Networks *Invited Talk

2019 Winnipeg, CA Indigenous Services Canada, NIITA

Youth Engagement through Project-Based Learning *Invited Talk

2019 Montreal, CA English Montreal School Board Teachers' Professional Development

Stochastic Gradient Push for Distributed Deep Learning

2019	Long Beach, US	International	Conference on	Machine i	Learning (ICML)
------	----------------	---------------	---------------	-----------	------------	-------

2018 Montreal, CA Systems for ML Workshop, NeurIPS

Convergence of Asynchronous Gradient Push under Arbitrary Bounded Delay

2019	Pacific Grove, US	IEEE Asilomar Conference *Invited Talk
2018	Limassol, Cyprus	European Control Conference (ECC) *Invited Talk

Open-Source Contributions

facebookresearch/msn 2022

GitHub Stars: >300

Code to reproduce results in our work on self-supervised learning with Masked Siamese Networks.

facebookresearch/suncet 2021

GitHub Stars: >400

Code to reproduce results in our work on semi-supervised learning of visual features with PAWS.

facebookresearch/stochastic_gradient_push

2019

GitHub Stars: >100

Code to reproduce results in our work on distributed deep learning with Stochastic Gradient Push (now implemented in the PyTorch fairscale library with over 1800 GitHub stars).

Selected Media Coverage

Venture Beat | Kyle Wiggers 2021

Facebook details self-supervised AI that can segment images and videos.

TechCrunch | Devin Coldewey 2021

Computer vision inches toward 'common sense' with Facebook's latest research.

SiliconANGLE | Mike Wheatley 2021

Facebook enables self-supervised learning for computer vision Al.

Software Projects

Hitch | Distributed Algorithms and Mesh Networks

2015

Media coverage: Farstuff Podcast ♂

Won the Google-PCH Hardware Hackathon in Kitchener-Waterloo. Developed a distributed mesh network with a tree-based topology management and routing algorithm, a Chord distributed hash table, and a distributed search engine. The goal of the project is to develop a novel full-stack solution to provide connectivity in remote communities. I presented a proof of concept at the 2015 O'Reilly SOLID Conference, and completed the first prototype in 2016. The project was featured in several media outlets, including an interview with the Farsutff Podcast.

Fletcha | Social IOS Application

2014

Apple App Store

Developed an iPhone application with a novel triangulation algorithm allowing friends to find each other at large outdoor venues or music festivals. The algorithm computes a triangulation angle in real time, rotating an arrow on the screen pointing a user to their friend. The application was available on the Apple App Store for several years.

Extracurricular Interests

Soccer

In my youth, I had the honour of representing the province of Saskatchewan in Soccer at the Canada Games and Western Canada Games broadcast on TSN. I also benefited from short training camps with Major League Soccer academy teams such as the Vancouver Whitecaps, the Montreal Impact, and Real Salt Lake FC, and competed in friendlies against EFL Championship academy teams such as Luton Town FC. I also played the 2012 and 2013 preseasons with the McGill University Men's Varsity Soccer Team.

Tennis

I also at competed at the Rogers Junior Nationals Tennis Competition twice, on one occasion as the second seed from the province of Saskatchewan, and on the second occasion as the first seed. I am a certified Tennis Canada instructor now.

Running

I also enjoy running, and spent a semester training with the McGill University Varsity Track Team in long-sprints. During the pandemic, I also discovered a newfound passion for leisurely long-distance running.